<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>A Blog about GCP, mostly</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 21:41:57 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 21:41:57 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gcp Resource Hierarchy 101</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2020/12/01/gcp-resource-hierarchy-101.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2020/12/01/gcp-resource-hierarchy-101.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GCP IAM Policy 101</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This GCP’s model for managing access to resources has three main parts: &lt;strong&gt;Who, What Role and the Resource.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To grant permissions in GCP, you combine the &lt;strong&gt;WHO&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;WHAT&lt;/strong&gt; to create a policy.  You apply this policy, or Bind the Role to a Resource to create scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: Member in Policies. Users and Groups are managed in GSuite (Google Workspace), while Service Accounts and the Identity Namespace are wholly constructs of the Google Cloud Platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Role&lt;/strong&gt;: A role is a collection of permissions. Permissions determine what actions you can take on a resource. When a role is assigned to a member, you grant all the permissions that the role contains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource&lt;/strong&gt;: Who, has What Role is applied to a Resource to affect IAM Policy. A Member is assigned a Role which is then bound to a Resource to create an IAM policy.
In GCP, Each Node of the Organizational Hierarchy is a Resource which can have IAM Policy Bound.  This includes the Organizational Node, Folder and Project Nodes, in addition to all Resources contained within a Project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next in the GCP IAM 101 series is the GCP Resource Hierarchy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//gcp/iam/101/2020/12/01/gcp-iam-policy-101.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//gcp/iam/101/2020/12/01/gcp-iam-policy-101.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>GCP</category>
        
        <category>IAM</category>
        
        <category>101</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
